Jeremy Springman

PDRI-DevLab University of Pennsylvania Updated December 2024 ☑: jspr@sas.upenn.edu ☐: jrspringman.github.io ♠: https://github.com/jrspringman ੴ: https://shorturl.at/ixTW8

I am an applied researcher helping donors and civil society strengthen democratic institutions and practices in aid-receiving countries. Currently, I serve as co-PI on projects funded by USAID and the Department of Defense, teach a course on data science for global development, and lead several other federally funded research projects. My research uses machine learning techniques including natural language processing and forecasting and causal inference tools including field and survey experiments. I am particularly interested in developing novel design and measurement strategies to generate rigorous evidence from projects with limited budgets and challenging implementation environments.

Academic Appointments

University of Pennsylvania, PDRI-DevLab

Research Assistant Professor

Senior Research Associate & Director of Civic Research

July 2024 – Present

July 2022 – June 2024

Duke University, DevLab@Duke

Senior Research Associate

Post-Doctoral Research Associate

Pre-Doctoral Research Associate

July 2021 – June 2022

July 2019 – June 2021

January 2019 – July 2019

Education

University of Pennsylvania

Ph.D. in Comparative Politics & International Relations	2019
M.A. in Political Science	2015

University of Pittsburgh

B.A. in Politics & Philosophy (Honors College) 2012

Refereed Academic Publications

The Political Economy of NGO Service Provision: Evidence from an Ancillary Field Experiment World Politics, 2022 (DOI: S0043887122000107)

The Effect of Government Repression on Civil Society: Evidence from Cambodia International Studies Quarterly, 2022 (DOI: sqac028)

First author (with Edmund Malesky, Lucy Right, and Erik Wibbels)

Oil Discoveries and Political Windfalls: Evidence on Presidential Support in Uganda Political Science Research & Methods, 2023 (DOI: psrm.2023.14)
Second author (with Laura Paler, Guy Grossman, and Jan Pierskalla)

Under Review

Aid Flows and Incumbency Advantage: Evidence from NGO Projects in Uganda

Fostering Civic Engagement in Polarized, Autocratic Regimes: Evidence from a Field Experiment in Ethiopia

with Sewareg Adamu, David Dow, Fitsum Hailu, Mesele Mengsteab, and Juan Tellez

The Effect of Government Intervention on the Operational Decisions of NGOs: Evidence from a Survey Experiment in Three Electoral Autocracies

with Erik Wibbels, Maria Nagawa, Graeme Robertson, and Simon Hollerbauer

Pushing Back or Backing Down? Examining Donor Response to Restrictive NGO Legislation with Lucille Right and Erik Wibbels

Foreign Influence by Authoritarian Governments: Introducing New Data and Evidence with Fatih Serkant Adiguzel, Mateo Villamizar Chaparro, Zung-Ru Lin, Donald Moratz, Diego Romero, and Erik Wibbels

Selected Policy Reports

High Frequency Tracking of Civic Space Utilizing Domestic News Scraping and Large Language Model Classification

Prepared for Swift Expertise and Grounded Analytics Task Order by USAID DRG Bureau November 2024

Forecasting High-Level Travel Advisories with Machine Learning for Peace Data Prepared for Swift Expertise and Grounded Analytics Task Order by USAID DRG Bureau November 2024

Zimbabwe Governance Indicators Analysis Prepared for USAID Zimbabwe

March 2024

Resurgent Authoritarian Influence: Evidence from Machine-Generated, Cross-National Data Prepared for USAID Analytic Task on Authoritarian Resurgence and Influence August 2023

Radio and Social Media in Ghana Assessment Report

Prepared for USAID Ghana

July 2023 (DEC ID: coming soon)

The Effect of Social Ties on Engagement & Cohesion: Evidence from Ethiopian University Students Prepared for USAID Innovation, Technology, & Research Hub

April 2023 (DEC ID: PA-021155)

Resiliency Cambodia Impact Evaluation Findings Report

Prepared for USAID Cambodia

August 2022 (DEC ID: PA-00Z-KBD)

Retrospective of USAID's Response to Pandemic-Enabled Democratic Backsliding Prepared for USAID Democracy, Human Rights, and Governance Center January 2022 (DEC ID: PA-00Z-6HN)

Policy Writing

Charting a Course for Applied Research in Peacebuilding

First author (with Heather Huntington and Erik Wibbels)

Forthcoming in "A Positive Peace: Towards an Evidence-Based Peacebuilding" (United States Institute of Peace)

Report of the Advisory Panel for the Governance of Human Rights Organizations

With Mohamed Arafa and David Siegel (convened by Dr. Hazar Yueksel for Amnesty International) SocArXiv DOI: 10.31235

External Awards & Grants

United States Department of Defense Minerva Research Initiative

Modeling Climate-Induced Societal Adaptation and Population Displacement with New Machine-Coded Environmental Event Data: \$1,600,000 with Erik Wibbels and Iriana Marinov

Open Society Foundations

Special Projects & Crisis Response: \$250,000* $^{with\ Erik\ Wibbels}$

USAID Democracy, Human Rights, and Governance Bureau

- Tracking Authoritarian Resurgence and Democratic Institutions and Spaces: \$890,000*
- Distinguishing Legitimate, Superficial, and Fabricated Anti-corruption Campaigns: \$46,690
- Central American Regional Media Project Impact Evaluation: \$75,554 (Phase 1-2)
- Zimbabwe Governance Indicators Analysis: \$37,894
- Swift Expertise and Grounded Analytics: \$500,000*
- Analytic Task on Authoritarian Resurgence and Influence: \$99,737*
- INSPIRES Flexible Response Funds: \$83,000*

United States Agency for International Development (USAID) Bureau for Policy, Planning, and Learning

Local Evaluation and Evidence Support (LEES): \$98,060

University of Antwerp

Foreign Information Manipulation and Interference: \$12,500*

USAID Ghana Monitoring Evaluation and Learning (MEL) Platform

Radio Station Managers Survey: \$30,000*

USAID Innovation, Technology, and Research Hub

LASER PULSE (with Mesele Mengsteab, Juan Tellez, and David Dow): \$250,000

USAID Mission to Cambodia

Local Organizations—Movement Towards Self-Reliance: \$225,000*

National Science Foundation

2018 - 2019 Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement Grant (SES-1747642): \$14,996

Anonymous private philanthropic foundation

2018 Research Grant: \$38,600

American Political Science Association Centennial Grant

2017 - 2018 Grant Recipient: \$1,100

Teaching & Advising

University of Pennsylvania: Instructor

Global Development: Intermediate Topics in Politics, Policy, and Data Spring 2024

Course website: jrspringman.github.io/psci3200-globaldev/

Fels Institute of Government Lab Capstone Partner

Spring 2024

Local Evaluation and Evidence Support (LEES): Academic Lead

LEES promotes localization of USAID activities by building the capacity of local partners and strengthening networks that connect these organizations.

Recent Invited Talks & Events

U.S. Department of State (Washington, D.C.)	Nov, 2024
Perry World House Forum (Washington, D.C.)	Oct, 2024
Vienna University of Economics and Business (Vienna, Austria)	Sept, 2024
	- /
International Civil Society Centre (Remote)	June, 2024
Leibniz Center for Informatics AI for Social Good Seminar (Wadern, Germany)	Feb, 2024
Foris International Ethical AI Manifesto Launch Event (Remote)	Nov, 2023
World Bank EngageFest Webinar (Remote)	Nov, 2023
United States Department of State (Remote)	Jul, 2023
Community of Democracies Enabling and Protecting Civil Society (Remote)	Jun, 2023
United Nations Data Strategy Community Series (Remote)	Jun, 2023
US Agency for International Development Tech Tuesdays Series (Remote)	Jun, 2023
United States Army 95th Civil Affairs Brigade (Fort Liberty, NC)	Jun, 2023
Social Impact Evidence for Impact Webinar Series (Remote)	May, 2023
Duke University US Army Governance Training (Durham, NC)	Feb, 2023
US Agency for International Development DRG Center (Washington, D.C.)	Feb, 2023
Vassar College Data Science & Society Colloquium (Poughkeepsie, NY)	Dec, 2022
Paris Peace Forum (Paris, France)	Nov, 2022
International Civic Forum (London, UK)	Nov, 2022
Big Data for Development & Governance Conference (Philadelphia, PA)	Oct, 2022
International Center for Not-for-Profit Law (Remote)	Jun, 2022

Invited Public Engagement

Amnesty International Advisory Panel for the Governance of Human Rights Organizations	2024
Foris International Ethical AI Manifesto Contributor	2024
3ie Civil Society Evidence Gap Maps Advisory Group Member	2023